Finding Aid for School of Information (University of Michigan) Publications 1916-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Information (University of Michigan) publications
1916-2006
University of Michigan. School of Information.
Contains addresses, annual reports, bulletins and course catalogs, directories, proceedings, and reports including the Library Science Study series. Also includes newsletters such as the Doctoral Students' Memo, the Insider, New Edition, News and Notes, News from the School of Library Science, Placement Bulletin, and SILS Update. Also contains a history of the Association of library science alumni and issues of their newsletter Alumni Notes. Also includes the publications of Beta Phi Mu - Beta Phi Mu Newsletter and Musings. Contains the Dept. of Library Science summer session bulletin.
9710 Bimu C26 2
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit. (Donor no. 4855 ).
The School of Information Publications are open for research.
The first formal program in library education at the University of Michigan began in 1909, when the University Librarian, Theodore Koch, began a summer program in "library methods." In 1918, Koch's successor, William Warner Bishop raised the entrance requirement for this summer program to a minimum of thirty hours of college credit.
In the spring of 1926, the Regents of the university authorized the creation of the Department of Library Science with Bishop as its chairman. Two degrees were offered: (1) a Bachelor of Arts, conferred after one year of work; and (2) a Master of Arts, conferred after two years of work. In 1930 a bachelor's degree was required for admission to the program.
Bishop retired from the department chairmanship in 1940 and was succeeded by Rudolph Gjelsness. In 1948, Gjelsness led a major curriculum revision which eliminated the bachelor's degree. Hereafter, the master's degree would be awarded after two semesters and one summer of work beyond the bachelor's degree. A doctoral program was also begun.
In 1964, Gjelsness reached the mandatory retirement age and was succeeded by Wallace J. Bonk. Bonk suffered a heart attack in 1967 and resigned the chairmanship to return to teaching. Professor Russell E. Bidlack, who had been a member of the faculty since 1950, was named acting chairman.
In November 1967, a panel of library leaders, which had been invited to visit and examine the department, recommended that the department be made a separate school. On October 18, 1968, the Regents approved the request and the change became effective on July 1, 1969.
Bidlack was named the school's first dean, a position which he held until his retirement in 1984. University Librarian Richard M. Dougherty became interim dean pending the arrival of Robert M. Warner as dean in April 1985. Warner came to the school after serving as Archivist of the United States. Under Warner, the school began to grow and change. The first visible sign of this came with the Regent's approval of the school's name change. As of July 1986, the School of Library Science officially became known as the School of Information and Library Studies. The name change reflected a changing emphasis in the curriculum and the changing nature of the field of librarianship through the use of computers and electronic media.
Warner left the deanship in 1992 to resume teaching at the school. A new dean search brought Daniel E. Atkins, an engineer and computer scientist, to the school. In 1996 the school's name was again changed, this time to the School of Information. This change reflected an even greater shift away from traditional library studies and towards the use of new information technologies. In September 1998 Atkins resigned as Dean. Gary Olson served as Acting Dean until December 1999, when John L. King assumed the deanship.
Administrators of Library Education/Deans
University Librarian
1877-1905 Raymond Cazallis Davis
1905-1915 Theodore Wesley Koch
1915-1941 William Warner Bishop
Chairman
1926-1940 William Warner Bishop
1940-1964 Rudolph Hjalmar Gjelsness
1964-1967 Wallace John Bonk
1967-1969 Russell Eugene Bidlack (Acting)
Dean
1969-1984 Russell Eugene Bidlack
1984-1985 Richard Martin Dougherty (Interim)
1985-1992 Robert Mark Warner
1992-1998 Daniel Ewell Atkins, III
1998-1999 Gary M. Olson (Acting)
2000- John L. King
The Publications of the School of Information and Library Studies are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications and Topical Publications. Some publications (or their successors) may no longer be available in print but are available on the school s website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. School of Information.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; University of Michigan. School of Library Science.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Library Science.
Publications:
Library science study.; Alumni notes.; Doctoral students' memo.; Insider.; New edition.; News and notes.; News from the School of Library Science.; Placement bulletin.; SILS update.; Self-study report presented to the committee on accreditation of the American Library Association for reaccreditation under the standards for accreditation, 1972.; Beta Phi Mu newsletter.; Musings.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Library Science.; University of Michigan. School of Library Science.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; University of Michigan. Summer Session.
Genre/Form:
Addresses.; Annual reports.; Catalogs, College.; Directories.; Newsletters.; Proceedings.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  Unit Publications include annual reports, bulletins (course catalogs), directories and several newsletters, among which is New Edition. The directory, Who's Here, is continued in the Information and Library Studies Student Association (ILSSA) publications record group. The series Library Science Studies will be found under the heading "Reports".
  - Addresses
    - Dedication of the School of Information and Library Studies by C.M. Vest, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Reminiscences in Librarianship and Library Education, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Admissions Mailings
    - Open Houses, Visiting Days, and Program Interest Cards, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1965-1990, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Connecting People, Information & Technology in More Valuable Ways, circa 2005; 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 1)
      (includes CD-ROM)
    - Courses and Workshops, 1947-1986; undated (Box 1)
    - Digital Tool Kit, 1997-2001 (Box 1)
    - General, 1970-2006; undated (Box 1)
    - Minority and Diversity Issues, 1973-2002 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins (Course Catalogs)
    - 1926/27-1993, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - 2007-2008 (Box 1)
  - Calendars
    - Calendar of Activities, 1977-79, 1991; 1997 (Box 1)
    - This Week at SI
      - Print version, 1999 (Box 1)
      - E-mail version (print-outs), 1999-2002; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Catalogs
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Alumni Directory, 1927-1991 (Box 1)
    - Faculty/Staff Directory, 1952-2000; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Fall Orientation Student Directories, 1998; 2000; 2001 (Box 1)
    - Student Profiles, 1999; 2003 (Box 1)
    - Who's Here, 1962-1984/85, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Flyers and announcements
    - Miscellaneous, 1971-1996; undated (Box 2)
  - Manuals
    - Admission Packet, 1994; 2003 (Box 2)
    - Doctoral Student Handbook,, 2002/2003, 1993-1996; 1998; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Masters Student Handbook, 1995-1998 (Box 2)
    - Media Production, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Orientation Packet, 1994; 1998 (Box 2)
    - Student Handbook, 1990/91-1992/93; 1994/95 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - The Communicator, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Crack in the Wall, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Degree Specialization Focused Issues, circa 1990; 2001 (Box 2)
    - Doctoral Students' Memo
      - 1974-75, volumes 1-2 (Box 2)
    - Doctoral Students' Memo: Current Research in Library and Information Science
      - Volumes 3-6, 1976-1980 (Box 2)
    - Insider, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - ISS News Notes, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Library Science Student Organization Newsletter, 1967 (Box 2)
    - New Edition
      - 1986-1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - News and Notes, 1966-67 (Box 2)
    - News from the School of Library Science, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Placement Bulletin, 1971; 1997 (Box 2)
    - SI@umich, 1997-2006; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - SILS Update, 1992-1996 (Box 2)
      [precedes SILS Newsletter]
    - SILS Newsletter, 1996 (Box 2)
      [precedes SI Newsletter, 1996-1997]
    - SI Newsletter, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - SI Newsletter, 1999-2002; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - What it is?, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Posters, 1996-2002 (Box 3)
  - Proceedings
    - Communication Revolutions, Information Technology and Libraries, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Ehrlicher Room Dedication, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Public Libraries and New Directions for Adult Services, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Programs
    - Continuing Education, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - ExpoSItion, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Recognition Ceremony, 1990-2002; 2005 (Box 3)
    - Mini-Courses and Workshops, 1982-1989 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-2000 (Box 3)
    - PEP, DFE, and Internships, 1995-ongoing (Box 3)
    - Scholarship Recognition Luncheon, 1999; 2001 (Box 3)
    - Student Projects Showcase, 1995; 1999 (Box 3)
  - Projects
    - The Connection Project., 2002 (Box 3)
  - Proposals
    - Program Statement for a New Building for the School of Information, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - The 1999 Cultural Heritage Preservation Institute (Box 3)
    - Digital Collectives in Indigenous Cultures and Communities, undated (Box 3)
    - Digital Libraries; Report of the Santa Fe Planning Workshop on Distributed Knowledge Work Environments, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Enhancing a New Design for Subject Access to Online Catalogs, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Evaluating Workshops Conducted by the School of Library Science, 1969 (Box 3)
    - The Future of Libraries and Library Schools by Dean Atkins, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Gary M. Olson's Interview with John Seeley Brown, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Information and People: A Campus Dialogue on the Challenges of Electronic Information, 1990-91 (Box 3)
    - Interim Report no. 1 for the Kellogg CRISTAL-ED Project, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Interim Report no. 2 for the Kellogg CRISTAL-ED Project, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 1
      - Early American School Books: A Bibliography Based on the Boston Bookseller' Catalog of 1804, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 2
      - The City Library of Detroit 1917-1837 Michigan's First Public Library, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 3
      - Michigan's First Book Store: A Study of the Books Sold in the Detroit Book Store 1817-1828, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 4
      - The American Book in Mexico: A Bibliography of Books by Authors of the United States of America Published in Mexico 1952-1955, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 5
      - An Introduction to American Magazines 1800-1810, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 6
      - The Nucleus of a Library: A Study of the Book Collection of the University of Michigan, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 7
      - The Bibliography of Philosophy: A Descriptive Account, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Library Science Study no. 8
      - Frank Leslie and His Illustrated Newspaper 1885-1860, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Long-Range Planning Report: Submitted to the Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Memorandum of Understanding: School of Library Science and Office of Academic Affairs 1977/78-1980/81 (Box 3)
    - NSF/DARPA/NASA Digital Library Project Annual Visit, 1997 (Box 3)
    - ...The More it is the Same: Fifty Years of Library Science Graduates at the University of Michigan, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Program Presentation for the American Library Association Office of Accreditation, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Self-Study Report Presented to the Committee on Accreditation of the American Library Association (Draft), 1989 (Box 4)
    - Self-Study Report Presented to the Committee on Accreditation of the American Library Association, nos. 1-2, 1989 (Box 4)
    - SI Advisory Board Curriculum Comments, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Three Year Report 1987-1990 (Box 4)
    - The University of Michigan Digital Library Project, 1994 (Box 4)
  - The Sarita I. Davis Memorial Lecture
    - Brochures, 1979-1983 (Box 4)
  - Symposiums
    - Conference on the Transfer of Scholarly, Scientific and Technical Information Between North and South America, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Information Access in the 21st Century, 1986 (Box 4)
    - The Information Symposium, 1991 (Box 4)
    - The John Seeley Brown Symposium on Technology and Society, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Optical Storage and Retrieval Systems, 1985 (Box 4)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  Sub-Unit Publications consist of materials produced by units within the School of Information and Library Studies. These include the Alumni in Residence Program, the Association of Library Science Alumni, Beta Phi Mu, the Information and Library Studies Library, Information Technology Services, the Library Associates Program and the Office of Student and Faculty Services.
  - Alumni in Residence Program
    - Addresses, 1969-1990 (Box 4)
    - Programs, 1980-1997 (Box 4)
  - Association of Library Science Alumni
    - Histories
      - It is Well to Remember the Beginnings: William Warner Bishop 1871-1955, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Alumni Society of the School of Information
    - Program Updates and Donation Requests, 1989-2001 (Box 4)
  - American Library Association (ALA) -- UM Student Chapter
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
    - Newsletters
      - Alumni Notes
        - Volumes 1-11, 1928-1962; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Beta Phi Mu
    - Newsletters
      - Beta Phi Mu Newsletter, 1974-1978 (Box 4)
      - Musings
        - 1973-1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Career Services
    - Career Placement Survey, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
  - Community Information Corps (CIC)
    - News Release, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Community Networking Initiative
    - Brochures, circa 1998 (Box 4)
  - Cultural Heritage Initiative for Community Outreach (CHICO) (Box 4)
  - Information and Library Studies Library
    - Brochures, 1989; undated (Box 4)
  - Information Technology Services
    - Newsletters
      - ITS News, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - Lavender Information and Library Association (LILA)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
  - Library Associates Program
    - Newsletters
      - L.A. Times, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Library Science Alumni Society
    - Newsletters and Alumni Awards, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - Office of Student and Faculty Services
    - Newsletters
      - FAQ, undated (Box 4)
- Topical Publications
  Topical Publications include materials relating to the summer session of the School of Information and Library Studies.
  - Summer Session
    - Bulletins
      - 1916-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Archived School of Information Website
  The School of Information Archived Website series documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the School of Information. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the School. The website series is arranged chronologically, with captures from 2002 and 2003 stored on CD. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Archived School of Information home page, 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the School of Information, 2010-[ongoing]
- Archived School of Information Website
  - Website capture, May 15, 2002; 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Website capture, May 22, 2003; 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Archived School of Information home page, 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the School of Information, 2010-[ongoing]